So today's דף daf is י"ד. yud-dalet. We'll just read the last
line from י"ג עמוד ב' yud-gimel amud-bet and refresh ourselves what the
conversation was. So we are now well into the discussion of פיגול,
pigul, which you remember was a major topic in זבחים, zevachim, and
in מנחות menachot it provides even greater opportunity to have interesting discussions,
not only about פיגול, pigul, but I would say using פיגול pigul
as a means to explore the certain relationships of the different components
of the קרבן. korban. You know, you have the קומץ, kometz, you
have the לבונה. levonah. How do these things operate, either
jointly or independently? So the משנה Mishnah spoke about, about what happens
if you have the two lambs that you bring on שבועות, Shavuot,
שני כבשים, shenei kevasim, and the two loaves of bread, and the
bringing of the two lambs allows the two loaves of bread to
be eaten. So what does... so the משנה Mishnah said, or you
have the two בזיכין, bazikhin, the two bowls of incense that are
on the שולחן, shulchan, and you bring those two bowls and they
allow the bread to be eaten. So one thing that this allows
for is an opportunity to discuss that old friend of ours about
מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mefaglin be-chatzi matir. We're not up to that yet.
If you only have the thought during one of the cups of
incense or only one of the lambs. But this first discussion is,
is which the debate with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is, here you
are, you bring these lambs and you're only planning on eating one
loaf of bread in the wrong time, or you're only planning on
eating one of the two columns of the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim
in the wrong time. Is everything פיגול pigul or just the thing
you were planning? By a קרבן korban we assume you plan on
eating even a tiny bit of the קרבן, korban, the whole קרבן
korban is פיגול. pigul. What's the case here? And רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei said it's just the loaf you were planning on. And the
חכמים Chachamim say everything. So what is at the core of their
debate? So logically you would assume, and I've just ruined the surprise,
this is how the גמרא Gemara is going to conclude, so if
you get frustrated along the way, know this is how we're going
to conclude, that everybody agrees in principle that פיגול pigul applies to
the object that you... not just to the specific, you know, like
if I'm only planning on eating a כזית, kezayit, the פיגול pigul
status isn't limited to the כזית. kezayit. The פיגול pigul status applies
to the whole object. The question is, how do you define the
object? Right? If you have a קרבן, korban, that's one single object,
even if you've chopped it up. And if you plan on eating
one piece of it, the whole קרבן korban is פיגול. pigul. But
if you have separate loaves of bread and you're planning on eating
one loaf, is it one object with all the loaves, or are
they multiple objects? And there רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says they're distinct
objects, so it's only the one loaf you were planning, and the
חכמים Chachamim say it's all one big object and everything is פיגול.
pigul. That's the simple sense of their debate. The גמרא Gemara tries
to make it, and this is what we discussed yesterday, a more
fundamental debate. The גמרא Gemara says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei does not
even agree that פיגול pigul applies to the whole object. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei would limit פיגול pigul to the exact thing you're planning
on eating. So if you had a קרבן korban and you were
planning on eating just
כזית, kezayit, let's say a piece from the right thigh of the
קרבן, korban, then everything else of the קרבן korban would not be
פיגול. pigul. The left thigh wouldn't be פיגול, pigul, even the other
parts of the right thigh, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that,
but the point is only exactly that part that you were planning
on eating, everything else is not פיגול. pigul. So the גמרא Gemara
tries to say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei fundamentally disagrees. And even
if something is one object, פיגול pigul is extremely local. As I
said, we're going to reject this, but this is what the גמרא
Gemara is working off of.
Okay.
What? He can't change his mind.
That's certainly true. After you've done the act, you can't change your
mind. The status already applies. The question is how broadly and narrowly
does the status apply? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is trying
to prove that even רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei agrees to the idea
to reject this. And it's going to prove that even רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei agrees to the idea that the status goes beyond. How
is it going to prove this? Because we have a ברייתא Baraita
that says that if you thought with these two loaves of bread,
the שתי הלחם shetei ha-lechem on שבועות, Shavuot, you thought like 'I'm
going to eat a כזית kezayit of both of them', meaning combined,
a half a כזית kezayit of each, then both loaves become פיגול.
pigul. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. According... who
is this going like? It can't be the חכמים, Chachamim, because for
the חכמים Chachamim to get both loaves פיגול, pigul, you don't have
to explain to do a half a כזית kezayit of each. You
can get both loaves פיגול pigul even if you do just one
loaf, it'll affect the other loaf. So it must be רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei that normally distinguishes between the loaves, but if you're planning
on taking a כזית kezayit out of both together, that brings them
together and defines them as one unit. Okay. But what do you
see? You see according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei that once you
define something as one unit, the פיגול pigul status applies to the
entirety. That in principle he agrees that the פיגול pigul status applies
to the whole thing that is defined as one unit. Okay, so
let's take a look at that. We'll read from the last line
of י"ג עמוד ב'. yud-gimel amud-bet. אלא פשיטא רבי יוסי, Ela peshita
Rabbi Yosei, obvious that this ברייתא Baraita that says about... the כזית
kezayis from both loaves is going by רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. אי
אמרת בשלמא חד גופא הוא, Ei amart bishlama chad gufa hu,
if you say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would agree that it's
when it's one unit that the פיגול pigul applies to the whole
unit, משום הכי מצטרף, mishum hachi mitztaref, therefore your intent to eat
from both loaves can define it as one unit and both loaves
can become פיגול. pigul. אלא אי אמרת תרי גופי נינהו, Ela ei
amarta trei gufei ninhu, now the top of י"ד עמוד א', Yud
Daled Amud Aleph, אלא אי אמרת תרי גופי נינהו, Ela ei amarta
trei gufei ninhu,
if however רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose always insists that things are two
bodies, they're always distinct, even if it's like one thigh of an
animal, every piece is distinct from every other piece, then מי מצטרפי?
mi mitztarfi? So even if you're planning on eating from both loaves,
why would both loaves become פיגול? pigul? Not only that, how would
you even have פיגול? pigul? You could never define it as a
כזית kezayis from one unit. He wouldn't have the ability to think
of things conceptually as one unit if they're physically separate. If he
does not agree to a principle that we can conceive of things
as one unit. So that's our proof that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
does agree that we can, that פיגול pigul would apply to the
whole unit and we can conceptually join these two separate loaves. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. הא מני רבי, Ha mani Rebbi, this
is רבי, Rebbi, דתניא, Detanya, השוחט את הכבש, Hashocheit es hakeves, you
slaughter a lamb, one of the two lambs of שבועות, Shavuos, לאכול
כחצי זית מחלה זו, le'echol kechatzi zayis mechalah zo,
to eat a half a זית zayis from one of the loaves
of the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, וכן חבירו, vechein chaveiro, and then
you slaughter the other lamb, לאכול כחצי זית מחלה זו, le'echol kechatzi
zayis mechalah zo, to eat a half a זית zayis from the
other lamb. Now one thing you should be aware of is although
there were two lambs and two loaves, they weren't paired up, it
wasn't a buddy system. Okay, so it's not like one lamb makes
one loaf permissible and the other lamb the other. Bringing up both
lambs together makes both loaves permissible. So here you slaughter one lamb
and you plan on eating a half a זית zayis of one
loaf. Another lamb and you plan on eating a half a זית
zayis of another loaf. We have actually two problems here. One problem
is, do the חצי זיתים chatzi zeisim combine? But we have an
additional problem. We have the problem that you only, you had different
thoughts at the different, with the different lambs. This is the case
of מפיגלין בחצי מתיר mapiglin bechatzi matir that the
each lamb does not change the status of the bread by itself.
Each lamb does nothing by itself. So a thought about one lamb
is only half of the act. So
you create פיגול pigul with חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, with half the
thing that only does half of the status change. Okay, so that
is why רבי Rebbi says you haven't done anything. You haven't affected
anything because you haven't had a פיגול pigul thought with both parts
of the act. Okay, it's a different thought with each part of
the act. So that's, so that's רבי Rebbi is going to say
that. Yeah, you better, you should write that down, that's going to
be something we're going to be discussing for the next week. Okay,
it's on the test, it's on the final, right. Okay, so רבי
Rebbi says, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, אומר אני, omer ani, I say,
שזה כשר, shezeh kasher, that it's okay, you haven't created פיגול pigul
at all. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say why
is that? טעמא דאמר חצי חצי, Ta'ama de'amar chatzi chatzi, because on
each lamb you only thought about a half of a זית. zayis.
אבל אמר כזית משתיהם מצטרף. Aval amar kezayis mishteihem mitztaref.
Let's say with each lamb you had the same thought. What was
my thought with each lamb? Lamb number one I said, I'm going
to eat a כזית kezayis out of the two loaves together. Right,
here are the two loaves, here's lamb one, and I'm thinking with
lamb one, I'm going to eat like a כזית kezayis taken from
both. And then I get lamb number two and I slaughter and
I think I'm going to eat that same כזית. kezayis. So both
thoughts were about the same כזית. kezayis. So I had the thought
throughout the two halves of the מתיר. matir. So it was not
a חצי מתיר chatzi matir problem, and that would be פיגול, pigul,
even though there is not a כזית kezayis from each one individually,
even if the כזית kezayis is formed from the two combined. Okay,
so our question was that we had a ברייתא braisa before that
said that when you make a כזית kezayis from the two loaves
combined, that it's פיגול. pigul. And we wanted to try to prove
that that shows that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose shows you can conceptually
combine loaves. So we're saying no, it's not necessarily רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. Here's a רבי Rebbi position which implicitly says the same thing,
that you can make a פיגול pigul by a half of a
כזית kezayis of each loaf by conceptually combining the loaves. Okay, so...
מפיגלין בחצי מתיר, mapiglin bechatzi matir,
yes, it's not מפיגלין בחצי מתיר mapiglin bechatzi matir because it was
the same thought with both lambs. Okay, מפיגלין בחצי מתיר mapiglin bechatzi
matir is the thought that when you're having the action that you're
doing, that you're having the פיגול pigul thought, is that action the
full act or half the act? So here you need to bring
both lambs, so each lamb is only half the action. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, אבל אמר כזית משתיהם מצטרף. aval amar kezayis
mishteihem mitztaref.
So it does combine. So you see רבי Rebbi is implicitly of
the position that you can combine a כזית kezayis from the two
separate loaves. Okay, fine, you've proved that, but now we still have
to understand what's רבי's Rebbi's logic. It's the same question. So the
גמרא Gemara says ורבי אליבא דמאן? veRebbi aliba deman?
Whose opinion in this רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבנן Rabanan debate
is רבי Rebbi going by? אי אליבא דרבנן, Ei aliba deRabanan,
if he's going like the רבנן, Rabanan, meaning we're just going to
repeat what we said before. אי אליבא דרבנן אפילו באחת מהן נמי,
Ei aliba deRabanan afilu be'achas mehen nami, why would It only becomes
to get both loaves פיגול, pigul, it's sufficient to have a thought
about one loaf, right? The Rabbis say if you have a thought
about one loaf, you define both loaves as פיגול. pigul. So why
would רבי Rebbe say that to get both loaves פיגול pigul you
need to get a half of a כזית kezayis out of each?
You have to bring them together. Obviously he's not going like the
Rabbis, he's going like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, that generally says it
only applies to one loaf, and the only way you get פיגול
pigul on both is by planning on eating a little bit of
each.
So the גמרא Gemara says אפילו באחת מהן נמי. afilu b'achas meihen
nami. אי אליבא דרבי יוסי, Ei aliba d'Rabbi Yose, הדרא קושיא לדוכתה.
hadra kusha l'duchta.
Our question goes back to its place. Now this is a very
classic Talmudic phrase, which you know was often adopted in later rabbinic
writing as well. הדרא קושיא לדוכתה, hadra kusha l'duchta, which means, you
know, you just, you know, the question just comes back. It's sort
of almost like saying it's circular, but it's saying like you haven't
solved the problem. If you do, if you say this then we
just get back to our earlier question. Often this is abbreviated in
like, you know, some תשובה teshuvah writing or whatever, חידוש chiddush writing
as ה"ד"ל, hei daled lamed, הדרא קושיא לדוכתה, hadra kusha l'duchta, or
ה"ד"ק"ל. hei daled kuf lamed. הדרא קושיא לדוכתה. hadra kusha l'duchta. Okay?
So that's like a, that's like just an idiomatic expression. But it
means the question returns to its place. Meaning okay, but fine. I
tried to prove to you that it was a, the ברייתא braisa
was רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and it said a half of a
כזית kezayis of each and that makes פיגול. pigul. And I wanted
to prove from that that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would agree that
you can conceptually create two separate things as one unit. You're telling
me it's רבי. Rebbe. That doesn't solve the problem. How does רבי
Rebbe side with the debate of רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יוסי? Rabbi
Yose? If he's going like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it again proves
the same point that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says that you can
conceptually have the idea of creating a larger unit by פיגול. pigul.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
לעולם אליבא דרבנן. L'olam aliba d'Rabbanan. No, it's not רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, it's the
Rabbis. ולא תימא עד שיפגל בשתיהן. v'lo teima ad sheyifagel bishteihen. The
point of רבי Rebbe is not to tell me or the point
of the רבנן Rabbanan back here is not to tell me that
the only way to get פיגול pigul of both loaves is to
create to a half of a כזית kezayis of each and conceptually
bring them together. You don't need that for the רבנן. Rabbanan. Even
a כזית kezayis of one makes both loaves פיגול. pigul. אלא אימא
עד שיפגל בשניהם. Ela eima ad sheyifagel bishneihen. But you should read
it rather אלא אימא עד שיפגל בשניהם. Ela eima ad sheyifagel bishneihen.
Now what is the difference between the two? Don't say
בשתיהן, bishteihen, say בשניהם. bishneihen. בשניהם bishneihen as opposed to בשתיהן. bishteihen.
Here it really shows your sensitivity of exactly the gender of the
word. Okay? The loaves are, right, the loaves are, the loaves are
feminine, חלות, chalos, or lechem, and the lambs are, are male, so
כבשים. kevasim. So you have to בשניהם, bishneihen, meaning they're not saying
if you want to get both loaves פיגול pigul your thought has
to be about a half loaf of, half כזית kezayis of each.
The רבנן Rabbanan say even a כזית kezayis of one makes both
loaves. But if you want to get both loaves פיגול pigul you
have to have that thought for both of the lambs because each
lamb by itself is a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. So I'm thinking
about one כזית kezayis but I have to think about them on
two lambs and only then do I effect פיגול pigul and then
it will be on both loaves. Okay, we're going to have a
little thing right here where you're going to really have to pay
attention to the gender of the word. Okay? So אלא אימא עד
שיפגל בשניהם ואפילו באחת מהן. ela eima ad sheyifagel bishneihen v'afilu b'achas
meihen. Huh?
So the אחת achas is because it's shifting back to the feminine.
So you have to have פיגול pigul thought for both lambs even
if it's only אחת, achas, one of the loaves. Okay? בשניהם bishneihen
even if it's אחת, achas, even if it's only one of the
loaves because that's the feminine. Okay, that would make
פיגול. pigul. ולאפוקי מדרבי מאיר, v'la'afukei mi'd'Rabbi Meir, to reject the opinion
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר מפגלין בחצי מתיר, d'amar mefaglin b'chatzi
matir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir will say in a משנה mishna coming
up you can create פיגול pigul with half of a מתיר. matir.
קמשמע לן דלא. kamashma lan d'lo. You can't create פיגול pigul with
half of a מתיר. matir. Okay, so our whole proof that רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose would agree that the פיגול pigul status applies to
the whole unit, not just to the narrow thing you're thinking about,
is that this thing that seemed to say a half of a
כזית kezayis of each, seemed to say that you could bring together
two separate units and you would have a concept of creating a
whole unit.
A whole unit of פיגול. pigul.
Of פיגול, pigul, of the thing that you're thinking about regarding פיגול.
pigul. But the גמרא Gemara says that you've read it wrong. It's
not saying that you need a, half a כזית kezayis of each,
it's saying you need to think about during both lambs and it
has nothing to do with the debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Now I just want to take a pause
here to mention a point that רש"י Rashi makes. Because the, the
obvious question that should arise to us is if we assume the
basic position is, which it is, that אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, ein
mefaglin b'chatzi matir, that you need the פיגול pigul thought for, you
know, if there's two steps of the process for both of them.
How come we say here, we've been saying all along that you
can create פיגול pigul when you take the קומץ kometz of the
מנחה mincha because there's actually another מתיר. matir. What's the other מתיר?
matir? When you're bringing the מנחה, mincha, there's the קומץ kometz and...
The לבונה, levona, right? So how does taking the קומץ kometz create
פיגול, piggul, and that's been our paradigm example of פיגול piggul all
along? So what about אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר? ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir?
It's just the קומץ. kometz. And the later משנה mishnah will say,
we'll have the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים
chachamim that if I burn... if I burn the קומץ kometz of
the מנחה mincha and I had a פיגול piggul thought, according to
the חכמים, chachamim, I don't create פיגול piggul until I also have
that thought when I burn the קומץ kometz of the לבונה. levona.
גזונטהייט. gesundheit. That you need to be burning both the קומץ kometz
and the לבונה levona in order to effect פיגול. piggul. So how
come our משניות mishnayot have been talking about just taking the קומץ?
kometz? What about the לבונה? levona? So רש"י Rashi says, and this
ties into another issue, רש"י Rashi says, "Ah, at the קומץ kometz
stage, there's only one thing. There's only the מנחה, mincha, the קמיצה,
kemitza, because there is no עבודה avoda of קמיצה kemitza of the
לבונה." levona. The only עבודה avoda of the לבונה levona is the
burning. So therefore, if you're doing a פיגול piggul thought during קמיצה
kemitza or הולכה holacha or נתינת כלי, nesinat kelli, those are things
that you get by the קומץ kometz that you don't get by
the לבונה. levona. The only thing the תורה Torah says by the
לבונה levona is it says burn it on the מזבח. mizbeach. It
doesn't describe עבודות avodas prior to that. So the idea that this
is only half is only half when I get to the הקטרה,
haktara, because when I'm in הקטרה haktara mode, the burning mode, I've
got to burn two things. But when I'm in the taking mode,
this is the only act that needs to be done at this
stage. Okay, now that's interesting because if you remember, there was a
whole question about whether a זר zar could gather up the לבונה,
levona, and to what degree was that an עבודה, avoda, and there
was an opinion that it was an עבודה. avoda. So why is
that not a problem of חצי מתיר? chatzi matir? So I just
put that, leave that question there, but רש"י Rashi explains that until
now we have not been bothered with חצי מתיר chatzi matir because
we're talking about קמיצה, kemitza, and קמיצה kemitza only exists by the
מנחה mincha itself. When we get to talk about the burning of
the קומץ, kometz, then we're going to talk about חצי מתיר chatzi
matir because there's the קומץ kometz and the לבונה. levona. Okay, so
that's a little intro to חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. Yes?
I'm still not clear. Is אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר ein mefaglin b'chatzi
matir or מפגלין בחצי
מתיר?
mefaglin
b'chatzi matir?
It's the debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says מפגלין mefaglin and the
חכמים chachamim say אין מפגלין.
ein mefaglin. Alright, so one more time.
Really sorry, I'm so slow. But if we're going to keep having
it, I just want to get it. So tell me exactly what
it means.
Okay, so פיגול piggul thought when your פיגול piggul thought the wrong
time makes the קרבן korban invalid. That's when you have it during
one of the...
מתיר matir is throwing me off.
Okay, מתיר matir means... מתיר matir does not... it's the same idea
as מותר, muttar, but what it means here is something that changes
the status of the קרבן. korban.
It changes it for not a good...
invalid? No, no. It means that when it's done correctly, for example,
when I do שחיטה, shechita, okay, that is a מתיר matir because
what it does is it now brings the דם dam to a
stage where it can be brought on the מזבח. mizbeach. So it
effected a status change and it allowed the דם dam to reach
its next stage. When I throw the דם dam on the מזבח,
mizbeach, it effected a status change, it was a מתיר matir because
it now allows the meat to be eaten and the חלב cheilev
to be burned. So those עבודות avodot in which you have your
פיגול piggul thought are called מתירים matirs because they affect... when you
don't have a פיגול piggul problem, they bring the קרבן korban to
the next stage.
But when I have a פיגול piggul thought,
then you're invalidating the קרבן. korban. But what... so the only place
that your פיגול piggul thought matters is when it's during a מתיר,
matir, when it's during one of these עבודות, avodot, okay? What if,
however, it's only during half of the עבודה? avoda? What if what's
going to make the bread, let's say of שבועות, Shavuot, the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem valid is bringing two lambs, and you had your
פיגול piggul thought only when you sprinkled the דם dam of one
lamb? So therefore, it was a מתיר matir in the sense that
the sprinkling of the דם dam of the lamb will make the
bread permissible, will effect the status change of the bread, but it's
not going to do it by itself. It needs the other lamb's
דם dam to be thrown as well. So throwing the דם dam
of one lamb is only half of the job, it's only half
of the מתיר.
matir. The punctuation of this phrase is either אין ein or not
אין, ein, but מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin b'chatzi matir or מפגלין בחצי...
mefaglin b'chatzi...
בחצי מתיר bachatzi matir is one phrase. A half a מתיר. matir.
A half a מתיר. matir.
Yes. חצי מתיר chatzi matir is one phrase.
So now I understand, got it. Okay. Sorry, I'm very sorry.
You have your פיגול piggul thought during
a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. A חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, right. It's
not a full מתיר, matir, it's a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. Right.
Okay.
While we're explaining, the לבונה, levona,
what form is it that you pick it up and throw?
So we looked it up on the, Dov looked it up on
Wikipedia, apparently it comes from a resin of trees and then it
hardens and it becomes like rocks, like it's sort of almost like
rock candy, so it becomes, you know, these like... No, I was
also wondering about that. If it's small, if it's like salt-like, how
do you scoop it all off the מזבח? mizbeach? But it's more
like it's more rock-like, like tiny pebbles, like tiny little hard rocks,
like rock candy.
So then you could pick it up and then you burn it.
Right.
And it makes a beautiful smell, right. Oh, okay. Okay? Alright, good.
So now we're saying that that was not רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
it did not mean a half of a כזית kezayit of each,
it said you needed to have the thought during both lambs and
it was the position of אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, ein mefaglin b'chatzi
matir, that you need that doing it for one lamb does not
suffice. Okay, so let's continue with the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא
Gemara is still not happy, it's still convinced that רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosi, you know, agrees in principle. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי מאי לעולם. ee hachi mai
l'olam. It's the line that starts with the word לעולם, l'olam, it's
about fifteen lines down. If that's really true that this משנה Mishnah
is, this ברייתא Beraita is saying, oh no, that wasn't a problem
because you don't have the thought on both lambs, you need the,
you know, having the thought on one lamb is not enough, you
need the thought on both lambs. Then why would it say לעולם
אינו פיגול עד שיפגל. l'olam eino pigul ad she'yefagel. Like לעולם l'olam
means like, you know, none of this is going to help until
you do a major change. If you're just saying you need both
lambs, just say אינו פיגול עד שיפגל. eino pigul ad she'yefagel. לעולם
l'olam sounds like there's a lot of things that were, you know,
classically have that have to be addressed.
מאי לעולם? mai l'olam? אי אמרת בשלמא בשתיהן ובשניהן, ee amrat bishlama
bishteihen u'vishneihen, you gotta love the sort of, you know, the terseness
of this. If you say that we're saying both are required, number
one, you have to have the thought from a half of a
כזית kezayit of each loaf of bread, that's בשתיהן, bishteihen, because only
then would it affect both loaves because you bring both loaves together,
like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. And you need it בשניהן bishneihen in
both lambs because אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir, you
need to have the thought during both stages. So if you say
you need to have two criteria met, אי אמרת בשלמא בשתיהן ובשניהן,
ee amrat bishlama bishteihen u'vishneihen, both breads and both lambs, ורבי יוסי
היא v'Rabbi Yosi hi and it's רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, ולאפוקי מדרבי
מאיר ומדרבנן, u'l'afukei mi'de'Rabbi Meir u'mi'de'Rabbanan,
and he's rejecting two opposing positions. Number one he's rejecting רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that says one lamb is enough because he says no,
אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir. And number two he
rejects the רבנן Rabbanan who say that one loaf is enough and
that פיגול pigul of one loaf affects the other, and he says
no, you need to have your thought about both loaves. So then
you understand why he's saying לעולם. l'olam.
So as that's what he's saying coming to do, היינו דקאמר לעולם.
hainu d'ka'amar l'olam. It'll never be פיגול pigul on both loaves until
you address two separate problems. You have your thought during both lambs
against רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and it's on both loaves, a half
of a כזית kezayit of each. Okay? So I'm arguing on two
people, I'm going to say לעולם, l'olam, you gotta address both of
those issues. אלא אי אמרת רבנן, ela ee amrat Rabbanan,
if it's all it is is the issue of if it's the
רבנן Rabbanan who argue on רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and say it's
only one loaf is enough, ולאפוקי מדרבי מאיר, u'l'afukei mi'de'Rabbi Meir, and
all they're just doing is saying that they're rejecting רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and you need the thought during both lambs but they're not
worried about the bread, מאי לעולם? mai l'olam? Why is it saying
it's never a problem on both? All they're just saying is no,
you need both lambs. So the first thing is the sort of
drastic language of לעולם l'olam seems to be showing that there's a
lot of problems that have to be surmounted if you want to
get פיגול. pigul. You have to do it both lambs and both
loaves, which again proves what? The whole thing we've been trying to
prove is that this idea of both loaves, a, the ברייתא Beraita
means both loaves, and number two it's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. According
to the רבנן, Rabbanan, if it's on one loaf it affects the
other. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said they won't, it won't affect the
other until you bring the loaves together and do it out of
both. But what does this show us ultimately? That when רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi says פיגול pigul on one thing doesn't affect the other,
it's only because they are physically and conceptually distinct. But רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi agrees in principle that if you conceptually combine them or
they're physically combined like the whole carcass of an animal, right, that
then פיגול pigul will affect the whole object. Okay, so that seems
to be proof number one, and the other proofs are going to
be more straightforward.
They want to have less פיגול, pigul, they want to make it
harder to have.
No, actually, they because by interpreting רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi this way,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is going to say more cases the פיגול
pigul will spread. That's right. But you mean, oh, their attempt to
interpret him more narrowly. Could be. But I'm not, but I think
there's a general assumption we wouldn't rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi.
Meaning, I think that whatever you might think in other cases when
we're talking about like practical issues like a שבת Shabbat debate, that
the the issue of, you know, practical implications might be informing how
you interpret a debate or how you, you know, and so on.
I think one of the interesting things about קדשים Kodashim is that
it's often hard to imagine that they're caring too much about the
practical implications because this is just so purely theoretical. So I think
it's more interesting to sort of think about, you know, how conceptually
are these things, you know, either make sense or don't make sense.
Now you might say otherwise if they're trying to create a virtual
world of קרבנות Korbanot and
It can't be purely conceptual because you have to be able to
imagine that it would be done. And the, I mean, this is
actually, I have found these pages really hard, I must say, for
it's hard on them
remotely.
It's hard because they're parsing it out so minutely.
Right.
And concentration and thought don't really work that way.
Right, which is also by the way why I don't think that
it's the practical issue because I think, you know, everybody asks when
we first encountered פיגול piggul in זבחים, zvachim, what is this ever
going to happen? First of all, you say you have to say
it out loud that somebody's going to say, a כהן kohen while
he's doing this, I'm planning on eating, you know, a half of
the כזית kezayit at this פסח pesach ta ta ta ta ta.
So that's why I don't think that whatever is going on here,
it's the practical implications of the problems that are posed. I think
it's a question about, you know, about conceptually. Now, the other question
is, well, what interested the rabbis conceptually? What interests you conceptually, and
I think that's a very important dimension that's often completely ignored in
גמרא gemara learning, is sort of like the religious themes. The psychological,
you know, sort of religious experiential themes. But I don't think that
even though I think that that's really often critically lacking in learning
גמרא gemara and being sensitive to the fact that that's going on,
but I don't think that's exclusively what's going on, right? I think
that a lot of what's going on is that they just see
this as a conceptual universe and they're trying to figure out, like
it's intellectually interesting and they're trying to figure out its exact parameters.
So I don't think it would be correct, as the same way
it's not correct to reduce every debate to a theoretical conceptual debate,
I wouldn't think it's correct to reduce every debate to a sort
of, you know, religious debate. Yeah, so it's important to,
like intellectually, the concept of מפגלים בחצי מתיר maphgilim be-chatzi matir is
a very interesting intellectual concept. Right. The question that I'm, what I'm
having trouble with is whether we're really applying it or whether we're
really trying to negate it.
Ah, I see. Well, let's wait till we get to this next
debate. Right now we're not at the מפגלים, maphgilim, we're just bringing
that in incidentally. The מפגלים בחצי מתיר maphgilim be-chatzi matir debate will
be explicit in a משנה mishna coming up. Right now the question
is when you thought affects one object, does it affect the whole
collection of objects? And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says no, and the
רבנן rabbanan say yes. And the question is, does רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose go so far to say he would even subdivide an object?
And that the גמרא gemara is resisting and it will now actually
very strongly reject. So let's take a look. Okay.
דהא אמר רב אשי, De-ha amar Rav Ashi, didn't רב אשי Rav
Ashi say? תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. I've got to
tell you again that this is a funny phrase. דהא אמר רב
אשי תא שמע. De-ha amar Rav Ashi ta shma. Normally, you know,
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, there was a question raised and רב אשי
Rav Ashi says תא שמע. ta shma. Right. So, you know, maybe
that was like at an earlier stage of the גמרא gemara when
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, this question was raised: what's the debate of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the רבנן? rabbanan? And רב אשי Rav
Ashi says תא שמע, ta shma, let me show you this ברייתא
braita to demonstrate the debate. But maybe at a later editorial stage,
the גמרא gemara is framing it like, I'm going to prove to
you this is correct, and now here's רב אשי Rav Ashi who
said that. So anyway, again, it's interesting the way this is enveloped
in the דהא אמר. de-ha amar. דהא אמר רב אשי, De-ha amar
Rav Ashi, didn't רב אשי Rav Ashi say? תא שמע, Ta shma,
come and hear. רבי אומר משום רבי יוסי, Rabbi omer mishum Rabbi
Yose, רבי Rabbi says in the name of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
So here we are with רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose position. פיגל בדבר
הנעשה בחוץ פיגול, Piggel be-davar ha-na'aseh ba-chutz piggul, בדבר הנעשה בפנים לא
פיגול. be-davar ha-na'aseh bi-fnim lo piggul. Now this is a ברייתא braita
in the ספרא Sifra in תורת כהנים Torat Kohanim about פיגול piggul
by when you do the חטאת הפנימיות. chatat ha-pnimiot. החטאת הפנימיים Ha-chatat
ha-pnimiyim or פנימיות. pnimiot.
Anyway, when you do the inner חטאת, chatat, you know, you sprinkle
the blood in the inside of the היכל Heichal and you take
the meat and you burn it outside the מקדש. Mikdash. You have
that on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you have that for the פר
העלם דבר par he'elam davar when the whole ציבור tzibbur brings a
חטאת chatat because the בית דין Beit Din ruled incorrectly. Those are
some of the examples. Would there be פיגול piggul in this case?
So one, if you remember the paradigm of פיגול piggul where the
תורה Torah discusses פיגול piggul is שלמים. shlamim. שלמים Shlamim is both
slaughtered outside of the היכל Heichal and the blood is put outside
of the היכל Heichal on the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. So רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose here, רבי Rabbi is quoting רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is
saying when you have this inner חטאת, chatat, it has to parallel
the שלמים. shlamim. And the only time you will have a פיגול
piggul is if you had the thought during an עבודה avoda that
was outside of the היכל, Heichal, in the עזרה Azara but outside
the היכל, Heichal, and regarding something that is going to be done
outside of the היכל. Heichal. So let's take a look at the
example.
פיגל בדבר הנעשה בחוץ פיגול. Piggel be-davar ha-na'aseh ba-chutz piggul. If you
had a פיגול piggul thought for something that is done outside the
עזרה Azara actually, in the עזרה Azara outside the היכל, Heichal, it's
פיגול. piggul. בדבר הנעשה בפנים, Be-davar ha-na'aseh bi-fnim, something done inside the
היכל, Heichal, לא פיגול, lo piggul, you have not created פיגול. piggul.
כיצד, Keitzad, how is this? היה עומד בחוץ, Haya omed ba-chutz, you
were standing outside of the היכל, Heichal, again, in the עזרה. Azara.
ואמר, Ve-amar, and you said: הריני שוחט על מנת להזות מדמו למחר,
Hareini shochet al menat lehazot midamo lemachar, I am going to שוחט
shochet this. how that's going to be burned, you know, this inner
cow, for the intent to do זריקת הדם zrikas hadam tomorrow. Now
where do you do the זריקה? zrika? Inside the היכל, Heichal, you
sprinkle toward the פרוכת. paroches. This is like one example this is
the יום כיפור Yom Kippur example. So if that's, you know, the
one that's most clear in your head, you know, because we read
the עבודה Avoda on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you slaughter the cow
outside, you bring the blood inside, you sprinkle inside. So if the
כהן Kohen slaughtered the cow outside and said I'm going to sprinkle
the blood tomorrow on the 11th of תשרי, Tishrei, not today, so
then that would not be פיגול pigul because he's planning on doing
something in the היכל, Heichal, not and the פיגול pigul has to
be done while you're doing an act outside the היכל Heichal with
the intent to do a certain act outside the היכל. Heichal. Okay,
why? Because we've just learned from the שלמים Shelamim as the paradigm.
I can't give an explanation, but I could
imagine that would be a real, a real pride, right, exactly.
So I guess logically doing
one on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur would have to be on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right.
But again remember the פיגול pigul thought has to be extremely close
to the right thing, but but slightly wrong, meaning if I say
for example I'm going to slaughter this קרבן korban and I'm going
to burn it, you know, on the floor, I'm not going to
offer it at all, that's not פיגול. pigul. Right, it's like completely
unrelated. Now here it's not absurd, I'm going to do the same
עבודה avoda I'll just do it tomorrow, not today, it's no different
than saying I'll do the עבודה avoda on the outer מזבח mizbeiach
tomorrow not today, but somehow because it's about the inner,
I agree it's a little bit is bizarre, it's ironic. No question.
Okay. So let's take a look. But it's because he's learning from
שלמים. Shelamim. So, כיצד, Keitzad, היה עומד בחוץ ואמר הרי אני שוחט
על מנת להזות מדמו למחר. Hayah omeid bachutz ve'amar harei ani shocheit
al m'nas lehazzot midamo lemachar. I'm going to sprinkle the blood on
the פרוכת paroches tomorrow after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, לא פיגל, lo
pigal, that's not פיגול, pigul, שמחשבה בחוץ, shemachshava bachutz, you were thinking
it outside during שחיטה, shechita, בדבר הנעשה בפנים, badavar hana'aseh bifnim, it
was relating to an עבודה avoda on the inside. היה עומד בפנים.
Hayah omeid bifnim. So now you're in the היכל Heichal on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and you're sprinkling the blood towards the פרוכת. paroches.
So you're doing the עבודה avoda of the דם, dam, ואמר, ve'amar,
and you said, הרי אני מזה על מנת להקטיר אימורין למחר. harei
ani mazzeh al m'nas lehaktir imurin lemachar.
I'm going to burn the, you know, the innards, I'm going to
the entrails I'll burn them the day after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
ולשפוך שיירים למחר. Velishpoch shirayim lemachar.
I'll pour the remnant of the blood tomorrow. So those are things
that are done on the outer מזבח. mizbeiach. Nevertheless, לא פיגל, lo
pigal, you have not created פיגול. pigul. Why? שמחשבה בפנים shemachshava bifnim
because you were thinking about it in the היכל, Heichal, although it
was בדבר הנעשה בחוץ badavar hana'aseh bachutz regarding an עבודה avoda outside.
You have to be thinking about it outside during an outside עבודה
avoda and about doing an outside עבודה. avoda. So what would be
the example? So, היה עומד בחוץ, Hayah omeid bachutz, ואמר הרי אני
שוחט, ve'amar harei ani shocheit,
I am שוחט shocheit this קרבן, korban, this this פר par of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur or this שעיר, sa'ir, על מנת לשפוך שיירים
למחר. al m'nas lishpoch shirayim lemachar. And I'm going to pour the
blood on the outer מזבח, mizbeiach, not today but tomorrow. ולהקטיר אימורין
למחר. Ulehaktir imurin lemachar. Or I'll burn the the innards tomorrow. פיגול.
pigul. Then you have finally gotten פיגול. pigul. שמחשבה בחוץ. shemachshava bachutz.
You had your thought outside when you were doing the שחיטה, shechita,
not when you were inside the היכל. Heichal. בדבר הנעשה בחוץ Bedavar
hana'aseh bachutz regarding doing an עבודה avoda outside of the היכל Heichal
at the wrong time. Okay. So that's basically a ברייתא. braisa. Now
how is that at all relevant to our debate of whether it
applies to the whole unit or piece of it? So here's how
the גמרא Gemara will ingeniously derive how it's relevant to our debate.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says the following.
לשפוך שיירים לפלוגי מאי. Lishpoch shirayim liflugei mai.
When you are having this thought and I'm going to slaughter it
to pour the שיירים shirayim tomorrow, what is going to become פיגול?
pigul? Why what's the question? לפלוגי מאי. Liflugei mai. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אילימא לפלוגי דם. ileima liflugei dam.
Okay the דם dam will be פיגול. pigul. Meaning I got how
your thought is a פיגול pigul thought. You were doing it during
the שחיטה shechita and you were planning on doing the שפיכת שיירים
shfichas shirayim at the wrong time. But what is the relevance of
פיגול? pigul? The relevance of פיגול pigul is if now I eat
from the קרבן korban I get כרת. kares. So the גמרא Gemara
asks a very simple question. What's left to eat from the קרבן?
korban? What can I eat from now to get כרת? kares? Okay
the meat is burnt, the blood is sprinkled, the אימורין imurin are
burnt, what can I be eating to get כרת kares if I
have made this thing into פיגול? pigul? Skin? You don't eat the
skin. So let's take a look at what the possibilities are and
how it becomes relevant.
Okay. לפלוגי דם, Liflugei dam, should the דם dam become פיגול? pigul?
If I decide now to eat the דם, dam, you know maybe
there's leftover דם dam that I'm not spilling and I'm going to
now eat from it. Okay דם לא מיפגל, dam lo mipagal, דם
dam does not become פיגול. pigul. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a
משנה, mishna, אלו דברים שאין חייבים עליהם משום פיגול. eilu devarim she'ein
chayavim aleihem mishum pigul. The following things do not become even when
you had a פיגול pigul thought and your whole קרבן korban became
פיגול, pigul, the following things do not become פיגול. pigul. הקומץ, Hakometz,
the קומץ kometz that's burnt up והלבונה, vehalvona, the frankincense, והקטורת, vehaketores,
the incense that you burn on the מזבח הזהב, mizbeiach hazahav, ומנחת
כהן ומנחת נסכים, uminchas kohen uminchas nesachim, ומנחת כהן minchas kohen which
is all burnt,
or the מנחה mincha that comes together with... the קרבן, korban, ומנחת
כהן משיח, u'minchas kohein mashiach, and the מנחה mincha of the כהן
גדול, kohein gadol, והדם, v'hadam, and the blood. Now why do those
things not become פיגול? pigul? Because most of those, except the מנחת
נסכים, minchas nesachim, there is some question if we have that גירסא,
girsa, but basically all those things are מתירים matirs themselves. פיגול, pigul,
remember, you're doing it when you're doing an עבודה avoda with a
particular item, the blood or the קומץ, kometz, which is going to
validate the קרבן, korban, and while you're doing your עבודה avoda with
this item that will validate, so this thing is the מתיר, matir,
you make what's left over into פיגול. pigul. So the way פיגול
pigul works is it's a thought during the מתיר matir that which
affects the status of this קרבן, korban, and your פיגול pigul thought
makes what's left over into פיגול. pigul. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ah, but a פיגול pigul does not make a מתיר matir itself
into פיגול. pigul. It makes the thing that the מתיר matir is
affecting into פיגול. pigul. So you can never have a פיגול pigul
thought, so even if you've made the קרבן korban פיגול, pigul, the
blood doesn't become פיגול, pigul, the קומץ kometz doesn't become פיגול, pigul,
the לבונה levona doesn't become פיגול, pigul, all of these things are
not what's left over, these things are the מתיר matir themselves. Okay,
so you cannot have פיגול pigul on the blood.
What? No, I mean you can't eat them for other reasons because
you're preventing them from being brought on the מזבח, mizbeach, you know,
and other types of things, but the point is you're not חייב
כרת chayav kares for eating פיגול. pigul. Okay, so this קרבן korban
which is completely destroyed, what is going to become פיגול pigul of
this קרבן? korban? It can't be the blood. So let's keep on
going.
אלא פשיטא לפלוגי בשר. Ella pshita liflugei basar. But meat will become
פיגול pigul even though the meat is supposed to be burnt, it's
going to become פיגול. pigul. Okay, fine, so instead of burning it
you eat the meat. Now we've got a problem though, you did
not think about the meat. What did you think about? You were
שוחט shechting this and planning on doing שפיכת
שיריים shefichas shiriem tomorrow. So you were thinking about the blood. But
now what has become פיגול pigul when you were thinking about the
blood? The meat. So here you see according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, you could be thinking about doing the wrong thing with the
blood and the meat could be פיגול. pigul. So רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose obviously agrees that what becomes פיגול pigul is not just the
object you were thinking about, right? Remember that is a pretty good
proof, right, that when does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose say it doesn't
apply to another object? If they're distinct objects, one loaf of bread
another loaf. But if it's all one big object, one big animal,
and I'm thinking a פיגול pigul thought about one side, the other
side becomes פיגול. pigul. If I'm thinking a פיגול pigul thought about
blood, then the meat becomes פיגול. pigul. Okay, so clearly he agrees
that if you can think about one thing and the rest of
the object becomes פיגול. pigul. Okay, wait, let me read that and
then you can ask your questions. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא פשיטא לפלוגי בשר, ella pshita liflugei basar, the meat becomes פיגול.
pigul. So השתא ומה התם דלא חשיב ביה בבשר גופיה, hashta u'mah
hasam d'lo chashiv beih basar gufei, you weren't thinking about the meat
at all, you were thinking about spilling the blood at the wrong
time, אמר רבי יוסי מסגל, amar Rabbi Yose mesagel, that nevertheless the
meat becomes פיגול. pigul. הכא דחשיב זה בזבח גופיה, Hacha d'chashiv zei
b'zevach gufei, your example the left side and the right side of
the קרבן, korban, you're thinking about the meat itself just about one
part of the meat, לא כל שכן דפיגא בירך ימין פיגא בירך
שמאל, lo kol shekein d'piga biyerech yamin piga biyerech smol, how much
more so should an intention about the right side make even the
left side פיגול pigul that the פיגול pigul status applies to the
whole unit? That's the proof. Questions? Dov.
I'm not convinced. No, well it's a good... I was just wondering
about
ignoring
the what if this right thigh left thigh business for example. I
mean what if I think that
I'm going to keep an age steak from this
קרבן? korban? I'm not thinking specifically
from one part.
No, you don't say age steak, you have to think to eat,
not to leave over.
Okay you
think I will take a nice chunk out of this קרבן korban
and you're not being specific. There the גמרא Gemara presumably never doubted
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would say that all the meat is
פיגול pigul because then you haven't, you know, it can be in
theory any part so obviously it applies to the whole chunk. But
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is if you did think about
what,
does that get into ברירה? breira?
Not necessarily. But anyway the גמרא's Gemara contention was which it's working
very hard to reject, right, is that if you specify does it
still define the whole unit? It says look, if you're thinking about
blood it defines the meat, so if you're thinking about obviously רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees פיגול pigul applies to the whole קרבן korban
and his only reason for debating the משנה Mishnah was that they
were defined as distinct units, two loaves of bread, you know, twelve
loaves of bread, it wasn't like fundamentally one animal even if afterwards
you chop it up. Yes, James.
I was just wondering because the blood has unique relationship to the
whole...
I was thinking that you were going to ask that. Right, you
could say that
when
I think about a מתיר matir the פיגול pigul relates to a
מתיר, matir, right, exactly. You could say if the פיגול pigul relates
to the מתיר, matir, the blood, then it affects everything that depends
on the blood. But if it relates to the thing that I'm
going to eat, then one side has no relationship to the other
side. That is a very... That is a very good response, but
the גמרא Gemara is interested in proving otherwise. Okay, but we're going
to, we have other proofs.
It has an agenda.
Okay, well, yeah, it's pretty much convinced. I don't know if it
has an agenda, but it's convinced. But let's keep on going. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, עוד, od, and here's another proof that he would say that
it would apply to the whole act, the whole קרבן. korban. אמר
רבינא, Amar Ravina, אמר רבינא תא שמע, Amar Ravina Ta Shma, again
notice אמר תא שמע. Amar Ta Shma. Okay, רבינא Ravina said, come
and hear: הקומץ את המנחה לאכול שיריה או להקטיר קומצה למחר. Hakometz
et haminncha le'echol shireiha o lehaktir komtza lemachar. You did a קמיצה
kmitza on the מנחה mincha and you were planning on eating the
שיריים shirayim or burning the קומץ kometz tomorrow. So that's a classic
case of פיגול. pigul. מודו רבי יוסי בזו שפיגל וחייבין עליו כרת.
Modu Rabbi Yose b'zo shepigel vechayavin alav karet. The רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose would agree in this case that it's פיגול pigul and you're
חייב כרת chayav karet obviously. Why else, you know? Here it's all
just one thing. So the whole thing is פיגול. pigul. Now the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, but what is פיגול? pigul? Let's take a
look.
להקטיר קומצה לפיגולי מאי? Lehaktir komtza lifgulei mai? So when you're planning
on doing the קומץ kometz at the wrong time, you're planning on
doing the קומץ kometz tomorrow, what is becoming פיגול? pigul? It can't
be the קומץ kometz itself, right? Because that's a מתיר. matir. The
מתיר matir doesn't become פיגול, pigul, right? מאי? Mai? אילימא לפיגולי קומץ,
Ileima lifgulei kometz, the קומץ kometz becomes פיגול? pigul? קומץ מי מפגל?
Kometz mi mifagel? The קומץ, kometz, who said since when does it
become פיגול? pigul? והתנן אלו דברים שאין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול הקומץ
וכו'. Vehatnan elu devarim she'ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul hakometz vechulu. Right?
In that whole long list, קומץ kometz is at the top of
it. It's a מתיר. matir. The פיגול pigul status doesn't apply to
the קומץ kometz itself. אלא פשיטא לפיגולי שיריים. Ella pshita lifgulei shirayim.
So you're planning on doing the קומץ kometz tomorrow and the שיריים
shirayim become פיגול. pigul. So השתא ומה התם דלא חשיבי בשיריים גופיה,
hashta u'ma hatam d'lo chashivei be'shirayim gufei, you're not thinking about the
שיריים shirayim themselves, you're thinking just about the קומץ, kometz, מפיגלי, mifagli,
nevertheless the שיריים shirayim do become פיגול pigul even though your thought
was about the קומץ. kometz. הכא דחשיבי בזבחי גופיה, Hacha de'chashibei bezivchei
gufei, when you're thinking about the animal itself, the left side or,
you know, and not the right side, לא כל שכן lo kol
sheken certainly that your פיגול pigul status would apply to the whole
thing. And here James's question is exactly on point as well. When
your thought is about the מתיר, matir, it's not a big חידוש
chiddush to say that the whole קרבן korban relies on the מתיר,
matir, so a פיגול pigul thought about the מתיר matir affects the
whole קרבן. korban. When your thought is about what you eat, maybe
we could say it was only about this part, not about that
part. But the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is evident and the
גמרא Gemara says that in principle רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees that
פיגול pigul applies to the whole unit. The question is how do
you define the unit? And with separate loaves, he defines those as
separate units. James, what was your question?
A different example or still
doing some same conceptual example? The earlier case was about דם dam
and this is a case about קומץ. kometz.
Okay, so why did you need to bring the second?
I don't know, but both of them have the same weakness. Okay,
okay, so I don't know why it needs a second example, but
conceptually
it's the same, one had the case by an animal and one
had the case by a מנחה. mincha. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, ella amar Rabbi Yochanan, but the גמרא
Gemara actually does reverse itself, so rather רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
you're right. היינו טעמא דרבי יוסי, Hainu ta'ama de'Rabbi Yose, this is
the reason of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. He does agree in principle
that the פיגול pigul thought applies to the whole unit. But the
question is what's a unit? הכתוב עשאן גוף אחד והכתוב עשאן שני
גופים. Hakatuiv asan guf echad ve'hakatuiv asan shnei gufim.
When it comes to the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, in one way
the תורה Torah treats it as one unit, in one way it
treats it as two units. Now where does that happen? רש"י Rashi
says something which is not so
smooth. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. הכתוב עשאן גוף אחד, Hakatuiv asan guf
echad, דכתיב d'ktiv one פסוק pasuk says: תביאו לחם תנופה. taviu lechem
tnufa. It uses
one word to refer to both loaves, לחם, lechem, the bread of
waving even though it's two loaves. והכתוב עשאן שני גופים דכתיב שתים
שני עשרונים. ve'hakatuiv asan shnei gufim d'ktiv shtayim shnei esronim.
Okay, two loaves. It calls it one, לחם, lechem, and it calls
it two. Okay, and how about by the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim?
וסידרן דלחם הפנים ילפינן משתי הלחם. ve'sidran de'lechem hapanim yalfinan mi'shtei halechem.
Okay, that we just learn out from the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
So the תורה Torah conceives of these loaves as one unit and
as two units. So to continue, we're now י"ד עמוד ב' yud
daled amud bet four lines down. גוף אחד, Guf echad, so they
are one unit, דמעכבי אהדדי, de'ma'akvi ahadadi, that they prevent one another
from being valid, meaning that if you only have one loaf, you're
not יוצא yotzei your קרבן. korban. The קרבן korban requires both.
גוף אחד דמעכבי אהדדי. guf echad de'ma'akvi ahadadi.
שני גופים, Shnei gufim, two units, דאמר רחמנא האי לחודיה עבידא והאי
לחודיה עבידא. de'amar rachmana hai lachudei avidah ve'hai lachudei avidah. When you
make the loaves you make them separately. You don't like make a
big dough and break it up into two parts. You make a
separate dough for each one and you make the loaves separately. So
that's not yet telling us the relevance for פיגול. pigul. That's just
telling us how the תורה Torah conceives of it. On the one
hand you need both, conceptually they're one unit, but on the other
hand each...
Right.
Absolutely. Now look, a lot of מנחות Menachot later will be about
how the things were made. Here the גמרא Gemara is just bringing
this in incidentally to establish this idea of one unit versus two
units and give evidence. Here's the way it's one unit, if you
don't have one you're not יוצא. yotzei. Here's the way it's two
units, you make them separately. Okay, now we're going to talk about
the relevance to פיגול. Pigul. ערבינהו מיתרבין, Ervinhu mitarvin,
if you conceptually join them, combine them, like you said I'm going
to eat a half of a כזית kezayit from both, then you
have defined them as one unit because the תורה Torah recognizes their
status as one unit. דכתב עשאן גוף אחד, Dakasav asan guf echad,
so that's a legitimate way to perceive of them as one unit.
If I take a כזית kezayit from—half of the כזית kezayit from
each and I'm thinking of them as one unit, then I have
made the entire unit, meaning both loaves, פיגול. Pigul. פלגינהו, Pilginhu,
if I separated them, I'm thinking about only taking a כזית kezayit
from one loaf, not from the other, so I'm thinking about them
separately.
מפלגי, Mefalgi, not מפלגי, mefalgi, you have separated them, they're considered separate
units. דכתב עשאן שני גופים, Dakasav asan shnei gufin, that the תורה
Torah treated them as two. So basically what it's saying is רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi and the רבנן Rabbanan agree that when you have
a פיגול Pigul thought it applies to the whole object. The question
is, do we always look at things as one object? Right? By
a קרבן korban physically it's one object. Now by the way, there
might be stuff that even is physically not one but is assumed
conceptually to be one, like what is the story when you have
a פיגול Pigul thought on the קרבן korban does it affect the
מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim that comes with the קרבן? korban? You know,
but that's okay. We define an object not just by physical but
also by how they're viewed. What רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says is
by the שתי הלחם shtei halechem they're physically distinct and conceptually the
תורה Torah recognizes two models. So if you think about them independently
one doesn't affect the other. If you think about them jointly then
they're seen as one unit and one does affect the other. Okay,
so that explains רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. It's a specific debate about
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, it is
not a fundamental debate. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. בעי רבי יוחנן. Ba'ei Rabbi Yochanan. Okay,
so now we are done with how we've framed the debate of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and the רבנן. Rabbanan. In principle פיגול Pigul
applies to the whole unit. How do you define the unit? Now
we're going to go on with related questions. בעי רבי יוחנן, Ba'ei
Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked,
פיגול בלחמי תודה מהו? Pigul belachmei toda mahu? במנחת מאפה מהו? Beminchat
ma'aseh mahu? Let's say you had a פיגול Pigul thought with לחמי
תודה. lachmei toda. לחמי תודה Lachmei toda are the breads you bring
with a תודה. toda. There are 40 loaves of bread, 10 loaves
of each unit. So now we want to know how far would
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi go? Would he consider these things to be
separate units or one big unit? Right, because he had a פסוק
pasuk by the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. What about other cases? So
how about the 40 loaves of a תודה? toda? Is that one
unit or are those at least four separate units, each collection of
breads? Or מנחה מאפה תנור. mincha ma'aseh tanur. What do you do
by מנחה מאפה תנור? mincha ma'aseh tanur? Some of it you bring
as loaves, other you bring as like wafers. Is that conceptually one
unit or two units according to רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi? What's the
הלכה? halacha? So תני ליה רב תחליפא ממערבא, Tani leh Rav Tachlifa
mima'arava, so רב תחליפא Rav Tachlifa from the west, from ישראל, Yisrael,
quoted—from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael quoted the following ברייתא: braita: וכן אתה
אומר בלחמי תודה וכן אתה אומר במנחת מאפה. Vechen ata omer belachmei
toda vechen ata omer beminchat ma'aseh. So he had a ברייתא braita
that explicitly extended רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosi's position to
these other
cases. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi basically says, he takes his cue
from the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and what he says is in
all these other cases of breads, when the תורה Torah sort of
there's a
way to categorize them as distinct collections, then I will say that
one פיגול pigul on one does not affect the other. So you
have two columns of breads by the שלחן, shulchan, פיגול pigul of
one column does not make the other column פיגול pigul if you're
thinking about eating one column. You have four different collections of breads
by לחמי תודה, lachmei toda, you have two different collections of breads
by מנחה מאפה, mincha ma'aseh, a פיגול pigul thought about one of
those genres, one of those types, does not affect the other type.
So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would apply it consistently across different types
of מנחה. mincha. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, we taught: בשעת שחיטה
חישב לאכול כזית ובשעת זריקה חישב לאכול כזית. Beshe'at shechita chishav le'echol
kezayit uveshe'at zerika chishav le'echol kezayit. Okay, so now we are talking
about having a פיגול pigul thought for the שתי
הלחם—let shtei halechem me just double check, is it right? Oh no,
I'm sorry, no. By a normal קרבן, korban, having a פיגול pigul
thought at different עבודות. avodot. Okay, now this is different than חצי
מתיר. chatzi matir. It gets a little confused. Why is it different?
Because חצי מתיר chatzi matir is, this is one stage and the
stage is composed of—comprises of two parts. So the stage is let's
say both... burning and the burning comprises of burning the לבונה levona
and burning the קומץ. kometz. Or the stage is, let's say, that
let's say is the easiest example. Okay, that's a חצי מתיר. chatzi
matir. But let's say I've done the entirety of a stage, but
I haven't thought about enough of the קרבן. korban. So in the
שחיטה shechita I think about a half of a כזית. kezayis. So
the פיגול piggul thought was during the entire process of שחיטה, shechita,
but it was only about half of a כזית. kezayis. And then
during the זריקה zrika I thought about a half of a כזית.
kezayis. So the thought was during the entire process, but it was
only about half of a כזית. kezayis. So you see it's not
חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, it's having the thought during the entire מתיר,
matir, but it's only about half of the unit. Can the two
separate thoughts combine? A different, a different half of a כזית. kezayis.
Right, so now it's like in total during the עבודות avodos I
thought about a whole כזית. kezayis. Okay, so let's take a look.
בשעת שחיטה חישב לאכול חצי זית, beshas shechita chishav leechol chatzi zayis,
when you do the שחיטה shechita you were thinking about a half
זית. zayis. ובשעת זריקה חישב לאכול חצי זית, ubeshas zrika chishav leechol
chatzi zayis, and when you do the זריקה. zrika. פיגול, piggul, that
would be פיגול, piggul, מפני ששחיטה וזריקה מצטרפין, mipnei sheshechita uzrika mitztarfin,
because those two do combine. So now the question is what else
combines? איכא דאמרי שחיטה וזריקה דתרוייהו מתירין אין, קבלה והולכה לא. ika
d'amri shechita uzrika d'taryeu matirin in, kabala veholacha lo.
Some say this is only true that שחיטה shechita and זריקה zrika
can combine because they both are not just necessary עבודות avodos but
they're a מתיר, matir, meaning the שחיטה shechita brings the blood to
the next stage and lets it be thrown on the מזבח. mizbeach.
The זריקה zrika allows the קרבן korban now to be eaten and
the fats to be burned and so on. So maybe שחיטה shechita
and זריקה zrika are both of the same genre, they're both מתירים
matirs and therefore they can combine. Okay, maybe only those two because
they're both מתירין, matirin, but הולכה holacha and קבלה kabala not, that's
one possibility.
איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri,
and others say no, הנך דמרחקין, hanach d'merachakin, even these two עבודות
avodos that are very distant from one another, if the first עבודה
avoda and the fourth עבודה avoda can combine, right, then כל שכן
הני, kol shechein hanei, certainly the middle עבודות, avodos, two and three,
קבלה והולכה, kabala veholacha, can also combine. So here we have a
new idea, not really related at this stage anymore to מנחה, mincha,
to the question of can you combine a half of a כזית
kezayis of one עבודה avoda and a half of another. So we
have a ברייתא braisa that says yes if it's שחיטה shechita and
זריקה, zrika, and we want to know would that be, is it
only that case or even that case? So let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says in the first example they said שחיטה shechita
and זריקה zrika combine.
In the first example they said, but not the middle עבודה. avoda.
Why do they combine?
Because they're both of the same type, they're both a מתיר. matir.
The שחיטה shechita lets the blood go to the next stage and
the זריקה zrika lets the קרבן korban go to the next stage.
In the second half they worried about,
about the proximity, right, the sequence. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
איני, eini, is this really true? והתני לוי, vehatni Levi, didn't לוי
Levi teach ארבע עבודות אין מצטרפין לפיגול, arba avodos ein mitztarfin lepiggul,
that four עבודות avodos do not combine, שחיטה וזריקה קבלה והולכה. shechita
vezrika kabala veholacha. So he seemed to say you can't combine anything.
And we've quoted a ברייתא braisa that says that at least you
could combine שחיטה shechita and זריקה. zrika. So אמר רבא, amar Rava,
says רבא, Rava, לא קשיא, הא רבי הא רבנן, lo kashya, ha
Rabbi ha Rabbanan, it's a debate, yeah you're right, it is debated
and it's a debate of רבי Rabbi and the רבנן. Rabbanan. What's
the debate? דתניא, detanya, השוחט את הכבש לאכול חצי זית מחלה זו,
וכן חבירו לאכול חצי זית מחלה זו. hashochet es hakeves leechol chatzi
zayis mechala zo, vechein chaveiro leechol chatzi zayis mechala zo. So this
is how it connects back to our מנחה mincha concern. You שחט
shacht one lamb to eat half of a כזית kezayis of one
loaf, and the other lamb to eat half of a כזית kezayis
of another loaf. So that's a חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, right, because
each lamb is only doing half the job. So
in that case רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, says רבי, Rabbi, אמר אני,
amar ani, I
say that it's kosher. Okay, so רבי Rabbi says I say that
it's kosher because even it's פיגול בחצי מתיר. piggul b'chatzi matir. Where
are we? אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so there you see
that רבי Rabbi says
that two separate עבודות avodos don't combine. So אביי Abaye says what
type of crazy example is that? That's not a problem of two
separate עבודות, avodos, that's a problem of a
חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so אביי
Abaye says אימא דשמיא ליה לרבי חצי מתיר וחצי אכילה, eima d'shami
lei l'Rabbi chatzi matir vechatzi achila, that each one was only half
of the stage. Again the difference here is we're talking about a
full מתיר, matir, שחיטה, shechita, and a full מתיר, matir, זריקה, zrika,
and do the half כזית kezayis כזיתים kezaysim combine? רבי Rabbi was
talking about a half of מתיר, matir, שחיטה shechita of one lamb
without the other half, without the שחיטה shechita of the other.
So חצי מתיר וחצי אכילה, chatzi matir vechatzi achila, it was both
a half of מתיר matir and only half of a כזית. kezayis.
כולו מתיר וחצי אכילה מי שמיא ליה, kulo matir vechatzi achila mi
shami lei, he wasn't talking about your case. Your case was you
did the whole stage but only about half of a כזית. kezayis.
So I hope everybody's sufficiently confused. So we still have this that
we have a debate of ברייתות braitot whether you can have when
you have a half of a כזית kezayis in two separate עבודות,
avodot, two separate as, do they combine? It's not a חצי מתיר
chatzi matir issue because you did it through the entire עבודה avoda
but it was about a half of a כזית. kezayis. Do they
combine? So אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנן לאביי, amar lei Rava
bar Rav Chanan l'Abaye, so Rava bar Rav Chanan says to Abaye,
ואי אית ליה לרבי כולו מתיר וחצי אכילה, v'ee it lei le'Rebbi
kulo matir v'chatzi achila, one minute, he says, I will prove to
you that רבי, Rebbi, even if you had the thought during the
entire מתיר matir and a half of a כזית, kezayis, he would
not have a problem. What's his point going to be? He's going
to try to infer something from the lack of a גזירה דרבנן.
gezeira d'Rabbanan. So let me at least tell you what it's going
to be and then we'll try to read it. Okay, so here's
the point. רבי Rebbi says if you do it during one lamb,
a half of a כזית kezayis doesn't combine with another lamb. What's
the reason? It's a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. חצי מתיר Chatzi matir
is not a problem. So he says, one minute, if רבי Rebbi
would say that if I did if
I did.